{"tossups": [{"question": "Lewis Keseberg, a member of this group, was nearly lynched after being found with over $200 and a pistol belonging to this group\u2019s namesake. James Reed attempted to rescue this group, which attempted to cross the Hastings Cutoff after a late departure from Independence, Missouri. For ten points, name this group of pioneers that led a doomed 1846 overland expedition to California that famously resulted in cannibalism.", "answer": "<b> Donner</b> Party", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the alleged first game of this sport, one team dressed in handkerchiefs and turbans to distinguish themselves from the other team, and Rutgers beat Princeton 6 to 4. Lorin Deland invented this sport\u2019s\u201cflying wedge\u201d play, which was banned in 1894. In 1905, Teddy Roosevelt invited leaders of this sport to the White House to discuss its poor safety record; shortly after, rules changes supported by John Heisman made the forward pass legal. For ten points, name this sport in which teams once earned four points for a touchdown.", "answer": "American<b> football</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "For ten points, give this first name of the current President of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Vladimir</b> (accept<b> Vladimir</b> the Great; accept<b> Vladimir</b> Putin after \u201cmodern\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Eleutherian Gunpowder Mills were built in this state by a Frenchman. An asthmatic patriot from this state rode through a rainstorm to reach the Continental Congress. This state\u2019s city of Lewes was the site of the Swedish colony of Fort Christina. The company that would become Du Pont is headquartered in this state, which Caesar Rodney represented at the Continental Congress. The first state to ratify the US Constitution was, for ten points, what state with capital Dover?", "answer": "<b> Delaware</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This country renamed its capital after its then-dictator in the 1930s and built a massive cross-shaped monument to Christopher Columbus for the 500th anniversary of his landing in the Americas. When the only country that borders this country was led by Stenio Vincent, Vincent was too weak to ask for compensation after this country\u2019s troops committed the Parsley Massacre. For ten points, name this country in which President Rafael Trujillo killed Creole-speaking migrants from neighboring Haiti.", "answer": "<b> Dominican Republic</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A photograph taken by Yevgeny Khaldei in this city was edited to prevent accusations of looting and depicts a man waving a Soviet flag above a destroyed building. A structure in this city contains the mural\u201cMy God, Help Me to Survive This Deadly Love;\u201d that structure was once crossed at Checkpoint Charlie. In a 1963 visit, John F. Kennedy said he was a citizen of, for ten points, what European city that was divided by a namesake wall during the Cold War?", "answer": "<b> Berlin</b> (accept West<b> Berlin</b> and/or East<b> Berlin</b> after \u201cmural\u201d is read)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This city\u2019s tallest commercial building is One Franklin Square, which was granted an exemption to the 1910 Height of Buildings Act and reaches 210 feet. In 2017, stained glass windows commemorating Robert E. Lee and Stonewall Jackson were removed from this city\u2019s third tallest building, the National Cathedral. For ten points, name this city where every building is at least 200 feet shorter than a 555-foot monument to the first President of the United States.", "answer": "<b> Washington</b> D.C. (accept<b> DC</b>; accept<b> District of Columbia</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "Alonso de Avellaneda wrote an unauthorized sequel to this novel, causing its author to rush its second volume to completion ten years after its first volume appeared. The tale of a captive in the 39th chapter of this novel was based on its author\u2019s kidnapping by pirates and enslavement by the Moors. This novel\u2019s title character is bored of his life in La Mancha, causing him to take a noble name and become a knight. For ten points, name this novel by Miguel de Cervantes.", "answer": "<b> Don Quixote</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "This war was the subject of a controversy in which members of the 1st Mechanized Infantry Division used bulldozers to clear out fortified lines by burying enemy troops alive. This war\u2019s losing side attempted to retreat through Highway 80, the so-called \u201cHighway of Death.\u201d Norman Schwarzkopf was able to win this war within sixty days of the initial invasion of Kuwait. For ten points, name this war in which George H.W. Bush authorized Operation Desert Storm against Saddam Hussein\u2019s Iraqi forces.", "answer": "Persian<b> Gulf</b> War (accept First<b> Gulf</b> War; accept<b> First Iraq</b> War; do not prompt on Iraq War alone; prompt on Desert Storm before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s regime promoted the Stakhanovite movement and labeled enemies as wreckers. As opposed to an opponent\u2019s idea of \u201cpermanent revolution,\u201d this ruler promoted \u201csocialism in one country.\u201dThis man frequently purged Old Bolsheviks in show trials and eventually had Ramon Mercador murder his rival, Leon Trotsky. For ten points, name this Soviet dictator who succeeded Vladimir Lenin and ruled during World War II.", "answer": "Joseph<b> Stalin</b> (or Josef<b> Dzhugashvili</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This material was used to make the death mask of Agamemnon, which Heinrich Schliemann found in 1876. This material, which is heavily used in cloaks in a painting of two lovers on a cliff by Gustav Klimt, was used with ivory to create chryselephantine sculptures. The outermost funerary mask of King Tutankhamen was plated in this material, whose \u201cleaf\u201d is often used in art. Alchemists often sought to create, for ten points, what metal that makes up electrum coins with silver?", "answer": "<b> gold</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this longest-serving First Lady in American history, the wife of FDR.", "answer": "<b> E</b>leanor<b> Roosevelt</b> (prompt on Roosevelt)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Averroes\u2019 works are primarily commentaries on this philosopher, who originated the syllogism form for logical deductions and postulated the state of \u201ceudaemonia\u201d as the goal of human life. In a book named after this man\u2019s son Nichomachus, this man advocated finding the mean between extremes as virtuous. The Lyceum was founded by, for ten points, what ancient Greek philosopher who was a student of Plato?", "answer": "<b> Aristotle</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This state includes a region once known as \u201cNo Man\u2019s Land\u201d whose southern border is on the 36-30 latitude line. A proposed state named Sequoyah was rejected in favor of the proposal that created this state. The Treaty of New Echota provided land in what is now this state in exchange for land in Georgia for the Cherokee. Under Jackson and van Buren, the Cherokee were forcibly marched to this state in the Trail of Tears. For ten points, name this modern-day state that incorporates the former Indian Territory.", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 1664, British forces captured this city from the Dutch and renamed it to honor the original title of James II. A battle in this city started when forces under William Howe</b> <b>landed at Gravesend Bay and culminated with a daring (+)</b> <b>night retreat by George</b> <b>night retreat by George</b> <b>Washington. Peter Minuit allegedly purchased a portion of this city from the (*)</b> <b>Washington. Peter Minuit allegedly purchased a portion of this city from the (*)</b> Lenape natives for $24 worth of beads. This city, under the nearly created Constitution, was the first capital of the United States. For ten points, name this US city that contains Manhattan and the western tip of Long Island.", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (or<b> NY</b>C; accept<b> New Amsterdam</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this position held by the chief administrator of the United Nations.", "answer": "<b> Secretary-General</b> of the United Nations", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Note: two answers required. Disputes over a glacier between these two countries inspired the term oropolitics. A 1965 war between these two countries occurred after one of them launched the failed Operation Gibraltar and was ended by the Tashkent Declaration. These two countries were separated by the (+) Radcliffe Line, which has been superseded by the Line of Control and Zero Point. The Siachen Glacier has been contested between these two countries, which have engaged in (*)</b> Cricket Diplomacy in order to reduce tensions. For ten points, name these two South Asian countries that have fought four wars since 1947, when they were partitioned from each other in their independence from Britain.", "answer": "<b> India and Pakistan</b> (accept in either order)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This site may have served as a memorial to the slain knights of Aurelius Ambrosius, a place described as the Giant\u2019s Dance. 56 pits surrounding this site are known as the (+) Aubrey holes and may have formed a bluestone circle. William Stukeley speculated that this site served as the center of (*)</b> Druid gatherings, and it was likely constructed by drawing from the Marlborough Downs quarry. For ten points, name this prehistoric site near Salisbury, England known for its standing rocks.", "answer": "<b> Stonehenge</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Eighteen of these works, including ones \u201cfor France,\u201d \u201cfor Freedom,\u201d and for \u201cAirmen,\u201dwere commissioned by Cincinnati\u2019s Eugene Goossens in 1942 to recognize the war effort. A</b> <b>speech by Henry (+)</b> <b>Wallace inspired another of these musical works for Goossens, which</b> <b>Wallace inspired another of these musical works for Goossens, which</b> <b>was composed by Aaron (*)</b> <b>was composed by Aaron (*)</b> Copland and premiered at income tax time to honor its subject, the \u201cCommon Man.\u201d For ten points, name this type of musical piece, a usually short flourish for brass and percussion, commonly associated with the entrance of a royal leader.", "answer": "<b> fanfare</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>The Celeres served as the bodyguard of these people. One of these people was chosen to rule after lightning was seen around his head; his Servian Reforms allowed plebeians voting</b> <b>rights. The (+)</b> <b>Vestal Virgins were brought out of Alba Longa by the second of these</b> <b>Vestal Virgins were brought out of Alba Longa by the second of these</b> <b>people, Numa Pompilius. The first of these people (*)</b> <b>people, Numa Pompilius. The first of these people (*)</b> abducted the Sabine women, founded a city on the Palatine Hill, and may have killed his brother Remus. Lucius Tarquinius Superbus was the last man to hold, for ten points, what position as leader of an ancient city, first held by Romulus?", "answer": "<b> King</b>s of<b> Rome</b> (accept<b> Rex</b>; prompt on \u201cking;\u201d prompt on \u201cleader of Rome;\u201d do not accept or prompt other titles, like \u201cdictator of Rome\u201d or \u201cemperor of Rome\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>The institution of this festival was disputed by Quartodecimani, who instead celebrated it on the 14th of Nisan until the First Council of Nicaea set this festival to be exclusive of</b> <b>the (+)</b> <b>Jewish calendar. Nevertheless, Computus for this moveable feast usually places</b> <b>Jewish calendar. Nevertheless, Computus for this moveable feast usually places</b> <b>it after the celebration of (*)</b> <b>it after the celebration of (*)</b> Passover, to preserve the commemoration of the Last Supper, while maintaining its position on a Sunday. For ten points, name this festival held after Holy Week, which celebrates the resurrection of Jesus.", "answer": "<b> Easter</b> Sunday (accept<b> Pascha</b>; do not accept \u201cPassover\u201d)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Different models of this system legendarily contributed to Austrian and Russian</b> <b>miscommunication at the disastrous Battle of Ulm. Aloysius Lilius [al-oh-ish-us]</b> <b>developed one of these systems that was introduced by</b><em><b> Inter Gravissimas</b></em><b>, a (+)</b> <b>papal bull. The introduction of one of these systems in Great Britain in 1751 angered</b> <b>protesters who declared \u201cgive us back our (*) </b> eleven days.\u201d Julius Caesar set and Pope Gregory reformed, for ten points, what type of timekeeping system that includes 12 months?", "answer": "<b> calendar</b> (accept Gregorian and/or Julian<b> Calendar</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}